Hi, everybody.
I am Marcelo Matiello,
Assistant Professor
of Neurology at Harvard Medical School
and In-Inpatient Medical Director
at MGH Neurology.
Today, we will talk about
altered mental status
encephalopathies, which is a very common
cause of consultations in the hospital.
So now let's move to the slides.
So today, we will cover the
definition of altered mental status,
encephalopathy, and
delirium, and highlight
the differences of such definitions.
We will present the elements of
basic and advanced diagnostic workup
in cases of altered mental status.
And finally, we will discuss most
common and key uncommon causes
of altered mental status
that are seen by neurology
consultants in the hospital.
Today, we will start with a case.
And throughout the talk,
we will have moments
in which we will check knowledge and the
questions will be related to this case.
So I ask the attention
to the simple history
that we will present for you here.
So the case is of a 65-year-old man.
He was found by friends and was brought
to the ED with mental confusion.
At the time he was brought
by EMS to the emergency room,
he had no family member with him.
We learned by calling the
friends that two weeks ago he
experienced the onset of fluctuating
disorientation and forgetfulness.
And he also had some strange
behaviors, such as trying
to brush his teeth with his cell phone.
In the emergency room, the
vital signs were normal
and the neuro exam was non focal.
There were no meningeal signs.
The blood counts, the basic
metabolic panel, and the toxic screen
was negative.
So let's start by defining
consciousness or mental status.
Consciousness is a combination
of arousal and content.
Arousal refers to the
level of alertness.
Pathologic states of
arousal range anywhere
from coma, a state of
complete unresponsiveness
without any eye opening, to drowsiness,
in which a patient is arousable
but needs the stimulations
to stay awake.
Arousal is maintained by
various systems in the brain
and includes networks of neurons
in the brain stem, hypothalamus,
basal forebrain, thalamus, and
a number of cortex projections.
As you see here in our schematic
view, many different centers
are working together to
keep the brain awake.
Consciousness also
includes the content--
the content of the mind.
That refers to the high
level cortical processing
that allows for awareness
of self and environment,
and enables the interaction of a
human being with the environment.
The contents of the
consciousness is carried, again,
by many specific cortical
regions in neuronal networks.
For instance, as you are
seeing here in this figure,
there are areas of the
cortex, they are focused
on producing language, understanding
language, planning, decoding,
visual stimuli, and so on.
Now let's go on to more of the clinical
definition of altered mental status.
This is a term that is broadly defined
as a change of the cognitive function
or level of consciousness.
As you're seeing here,
it's a very inclusive term
and describes patients that have
either a change of the content,
of the level of arousal, or both.
Encephalopathy is more
of a specific term
that is used in some
cases interchangeably
with altered mental status,
and implies the diffuse process
causing change in consciousness.
Finally, another term that
is very commonly used--
delirium.
It's even a more specific term
and it refers to the acute change
in mental status characterized
by a deficit in attention
and the fluctuating course
with disorganized thinking
and/or change in arousal.
And now let's take a brief
pause to test your knowledge.